Okay, we resume. We're picking up on basically כו עמוד ב, Kaf
Vav Amud Bet, but we do the last line here of כו
עמוד א. Kaf Vav Amud Aleph.
So the question is how do we know if the יום כיפור
Yom Kippur gets you out of an אשם תלוי Asham Talui that
when you become aware of the חטא Chet afterward, you have to
bring a חטאת? Chatas? So we've been saying it's based on the
extra ידיעה Yediah that it says by the individual, the נשיא, Nasi,
and the ציבור. Tzibur. And that one of them, the נשיא, Nasi,
wasn't needed. אביי אמר, Abaye amar, Abaye doesn't agree with this. Two
lines from the bottom of כו עמוד א. Kaf Vav Amud Aleph.
אידי
לא כתיב ידיעה גבי נשיא, Idei lo ksiv yediah gabi Nasi, מיחיד
וציבור לא אתי. meyachid vetzibur lo asi. Had it not written by
the נשיא, Nasi, I would not have been able to learn it
from the יחיד Yachid and ציבור. Tzibur. Why? משום דאיכא
למיפרך. mishum de'ika lemifrach. מה ליחיד וציבור שכן אינן עשויין להשתנות. mah
leyachid vetzibur sheken einan asuyin lehishtanos. The יחיד Yachid and the ציבור
Tzibur can't change their status. תאמר בנשיא, tomar beNasi, would you say
the same is true by a נשיא? Nasi?
שעשוי להשתנות, she'asui lehishtanos, that he could lose his status, he could
get deposed as a king. But a יחיד... Yachid... right, so two
questions. First of all, יחיד Yachid can become a king. But I
guess the point is that the assumption is that a יחיד's Yachid
position as a יחיד Yachid is much more secure than a נשיא's
Nasi position as a נשיא. Nasi. But the other point is like
why should that be more of a קולא kula or חומרא? chumra?
רש"י Rashi says, yeah, it's not really a קולא kula or חומרא,
chumra, but when it comes to arguing from a צד השוה, tzad
hashaveh, any point of difference is sufficient. So Abaye says it's still
required by נשיא. Nasi. So how do we know this idea that
if you become aware after יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? אלא אמר אביי
מהכא, ela amar Abaye mehacha, from the following place. מכדי, michdi,
מצות מצות ילפי מהדדי. mitzvos mitzvos yalfei mehadadi. In general, by all
three of these sins, it says מצות, mitzvos,
and we make a גזירה שוה. gzeirah shavah. And we learn that
they're all talking about, you know, the same type of a sin,
a sin that you would bring a חטאת, Chatas, a sin that
you would get כרת kares for if you did it willfully. So
in general, we learn these three categories from one another. Once we
learn these categories from one another, the נשיא, Nasi, the יחיד, Yachid,
and the ציבור. Tzibur. כיון דילפי מהדדי, keivan deyalfei mehadadi, since you
learn them from one another, למה לי דכתב שלש ידיעות גבי יחיד
וגבי נשיא וגבי ציבור? lamah li deksav shalosh yedi'os gabi yachid vegabi
Nasi vegabi tzibur? So we're back to the point. Why would it
have to say three? Say once, it's all connected by גזירה שוה
gzeirah shavah anyway. אם אינו ענין לגופיהן, im eino inyan legufan, if
you don't need it for its own purpose, דגמיר להו ממצות מצות,
degamir lehu mimitzvos mitzvos, you know the גזירה שוה. gzeirah shavah. תנהו
ענין היכא דמסיאדא ליה בתר יום הכיפורים. tenahu inyan heicha demisyada leh
basar Yom HaKippurim. And it teaches you when you find out after
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, הודא דמייתי חטאת. hoda demaysi Chatas. Then you
bring the חטאת Chatas even though יום כיפור Yom Kippur got you
out of the אשם תלוי, Asham Talui, that never really wiped away
the sin, and when you become aware after יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
you still have to bring a חטאת. Chatas. So גמרא Gemara said,
אימא כי מסיאדא ליה בתר יום הכיפורים הוא דמייתי חטאת, eima ki
misyada leh basar Yom HaKippurim hu demaysi Chatas, משום דיום הכיפורים לאו
אדעתא דחטא אתי. mishum deYom HaKippurim lav ada'ata decheit asi.
Maybe I should say that yes, the...
meaning now we're going to get to another question. How do you
know, forget יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, how do you know the basic
rule that after an אשם תלוי, Asham Talui, if you find out
you still have to bring? Maybe the אשם תלוי Asham Talui should
do that job, should wipe away the sin. So the גמרא's Gemara
going to say that. Maybe by יום כיפור Yom Kippur you still
have to know if you find out after because יום כיפור Yom
Kippur wasn't specific to your particular sin. It was a very generic
כפרה. kapparah. So there, afterwards if you find out you have to
bring it.
אבל אשם תלוי, aval Asham Talui, if you've brought an אשם תלוי,
Asham Talui, דעל דעתא דחטא אתי, de'al da'ata decheit asi, that you
bring it specifically for this sin. אימא הכי נמי דמכפר דכי מסיאדא
ליה בתר דקמייתי אשם תלוי לא מייתי חטאת. eima hachi nami demichaper
deki misyada leh basar dekamaysi Asham Talui lo maysi Chatas. Maybe it
really atones for you, and if you find out after you've brought
an אשם תלוי, Asham Talui, maybe you don't have to bring a
חטאת. Chatas.
You brought an אשם תלוי
Asham Talui and then you found out. No, forget יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. Along with יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, now we're asking a question
that we've assumed as a rule, but we're raising it, how do
we know it? How do we know the rule that we've assumed,
that if you find out after an אשם תלוי, Asham Talui, you
still bring the חטאת? Chatas? Maybe the אשם תלוי Asham Talui should
atone for the sin. So אמר רבא אמר קרא או הודע אליו
מכל מקום. amar Rava amar kra o hodah elav mikol makom. Now
of course what you could have said, which is an interesting insight,
is according to Abaye you have two extra הודע. hodas. You could
have only... it only needed to say one and you link it
all by גזירה שוה, gzeirah shavah, so two of them are extra.
So maybe one of the extras is telling you this, that even
after אשם תלוי. Asham Talui. But the גמרא Gemara for some reason
doesn't say that, and Rava seems to learn it from the word
או הודע, o hodah, which somehow seems to emphasize the או, o,
not exactly clear how, that in whatever case you find out afterward,
even after אשם תלוי, Asham Talui, you would still bring it.
Are you going to say אשם תלוי Asham Talui plus יום כיפור
Yom Kippur would clean the slate?
No. אשם תלוי Asham Talui is just... יום כיפור Yom Kippur is
just equivalent to אשם תלוי. Asham Talui. השתא דאמרת כי מסיאדא ליה
מייתי חטאת, hashta de'amrat ki misyada leh maysi Chatas, now that you
say that when you become aware afterward you bring the חטאת, Chatas,
אשם תלוי למה בא? Asham Talui lamah ba? So we really had
this discussion, you know, yesterday as well, but here it's sort of
and it was framed the same way. You know, if the אשם
תלוי Asham Talui does not atone for the sin, and the evidence
being that you still have to bring a חטאת, Chatas, how do
we understand how it functions? So we knew רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer
says you could bring it whenever you want, so if we're quoting
him it functions in some way as dealing with your sense of
guilt. Okay, but how do we understand that if it... otherwise, if
you can't bring it whenever you want, how does it function if
it doesn't atone the sin? So אמר רבי זירא שאם מת מת
בלא עון. amar Rabbi Zera she'im meis meis belo avon. No, it
atones for the sin in case you never wind up bringing a
חטאת. Chatas. Okay, if you never wind up bringing a חטאת, Chatas,
so if you actually definitely sinned, then you have to deal with
that. But if you never find out, then it atones. achieves atonement
for if you die in that state. So מתקיף לה רבא, Maskif
leh Rava, so Rava asks, מת? Meis? If he died, מיתה ממרקת,
Misah memarekes, the death will atone for your sin, why do you
need אשם תלוי? Asham Taluy? Okay? So how do you understand this
idea that it atones but it really doesn't atone because you'll have
to still bring the חטאת? Chatas? אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava,
and this is what we said earlier, להגין עליו מן היסורין. lehagin
alav min hayissurin. It protects you from being punished, it doesn't as
you would address the sin, the sin remains if it was done,
but it saves you from punishment, it addresses your state of guilt.
Okay, and then יום כיפור Yom Kippur comes and יום כיפור Yom
Kippur would take care of that anyway.
And then יום כיפור Yom Kippur is מגן משום היסורין. magen mishum
hayissurin. Correct. Okay, but again the emphasis is that it's not focused
on the sin, it doesn't wipe off the sin, it does something
else. It deals with your sense of guilt according to רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar or deals with the reality of your guilt that deserves
punishment, but not actually with the sin. So if you become aware
afterwards you still have to bring it.
That's not necessarily all that satisfying because it's still mandated because let's
say I say, alright, you know what, I'll take my chances on
roll the dice and you know let God inflict upon
me whatever he feels like. Okay, but the same is true about
a חטאת. Chatas. Why do I, let's say I don't want to
bring the חטאת, Chatas, I don't want to be atoned for it.
So that actually was an interesting discussion that we have whether חובת
חטאות ואשמות היו ממשכנין אותן chovas chatas veashamos hayu memashkenin osan or
not. Do we leave it up to you to decide whether you
want to get that atonement? Okay, so let's take a look how
the גמרא Gemara continues, as the משנה, Mishnah, now we go on
to the next stage of the משנה. Mishnah. Now we double back
to a point that was funny, this idea of the woman who
doesn't know if she's, if she has to bring her קרבן Korban
whether she's given childbirth. That was dealt with like that, you know,
the two scenarios were split up over two distant משניות. Mishnayos. One
said that she brought her חטאת מספק Chatas misafek then she became
aware before the מליקה melikah that she definitely had given childbirth, so
it says fine, then continue to do the חטאת Chatas as a
ודאי vadai because it's the same birth. The our משנה Mishnah said
if after she did it she became aware that she had not
had childbirth, then once, you know, then you have to bury it,
then it turns out to have been חולין בעזרה. chullin ba'azarah. So
let's take a look. חטאת העוף הבאה על הספק. Chatas ha'of haba'ah
al hasafek. אמר רב, Amar Rav, so רב Rav says, וכיפר vechipper
or וכיפרה, vechipperah, she achieves her atonement. Now that seems bizarre because
we're talking about a case that she didn't have, that she didn't
have a child. So who needs to atone? What does that even
mean? It's חולין בעזרה, chullin ba'azarah, how could it mean even it's
a good קרבן? Korban? It's חולין בעזרה, chullin ba'azarah, she didn't have
a child. So let's take a look. אי הכי, Ei hachi, the
גמרא Gemara says if that's true, אמאי תקבר, amai tikaveir, why do
you bury it? לפי שאינה משתמרת, lefi she'einah mishtameres, because even though
it's a good קרבן, Korban, you're not guarding it. Since it's, what's
the הלכה halachah about a חטאת עוף הבאה על הספק? Chatas of
haba'ah al hasafek? It's not eaten. So nobody is protecting it from
טומאה. tumah. So therefore even if it turns out to have been
okay,
since nobody was paying attention to it, you can't eat it. Now
all this is bizarre, why is it turning out to have been
okay? So it seems like that רבא Rava is going on or
interpreting our משנה. Mishnah. Our משנה Mishnah was a little vague. Our
משנה Mishnah says when she is נודע, noda, it is, she has
to bury it. נודע Noda that what? So it sounds like he
was understanding נודע noda that she is obligated. Okay, we'll see what
the גמרא Gemara does with it. But then he'd say, oh, so
if it's נודע noda she is obligated, then it actually did work.
But you still have to bury it because people weren't guarding it
right from the moment of שחיטה, shechting, till the moment that you
found out, right, it was, it turns out it was כשר kosher
because she actually was obligated and it could in theory be eaten.
But since there was a gap of time till you knew that
it could be eaten, in that period of time nobody was protecting
it from becoming טמא tamei and therefore don't eat it.
I don't understand that, but why do you assume it did become
טמא? tamei? This is the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash after all. I
know, but the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash everyone's really,
I understand, but there are other הלכות halachos about basically about like,
you know, about on the one hand people are מקפיד, makpid, which
is what the גמרא Gemara is going to answer, but on the
other hand there are all these הלכות halachos about היסח הדעת hesech
hadaas and about because it's קדשים kodashim and whatever you have to
be very concerned. No, no, but just have to be very concerned
that if you stop paying attention something could have happened. But you're
just saying nobody did stop, so that's what the גמרא Gemara says.
So the
גמרא Gemara says, אימת לא משתמרת, eimas lo mishtameres, when is it
not being protected? אי מעיקרא, ei mei'ikara, if before it was שחט,
shechted, חיה היא, chayah hi, it was alive and it can't become
טמא. tamei. אי לבסוף, ei levasof, if after it was done the
מליקה, melikah, קא מנטר לה, ka minatar lah, you were protecting it.
Even if you're not going to eat it, you're going to protect
it from becoming טמא, tamei, like Michael said. Who says you're not
protecting it? Okay, but it seems clear that רבא Rava was understanding,
although that was an interesting read, you bury it because you assume
it becomes טמא, tamei, he was understanding that she found out that
she had given birth. Okay, but now let's, but now let's take
a look what the גמרא Gemara does. אלא מתניתין בנודע לה דלא
ילדה. Ella masnisin benoda lah delo yaldah. No, that's not פשט. pshat.
Our משנה Mishnah is she found out she didn't give birth. And
the reason you bury it is because it's חולין בעזרה. chullin ba'azarah.
Okay, ובדין הוא דמותרת בהנאה, uvedin hu demuteres bahana'ah,
and really therefore it should be allowed בהנאה bahana'ah because it's, you
don't have to bury it, it's real, now, now, now, now, now,
okay, let's just read this. ובדין הוא דמותרת בהנאה, uvedin hu demuteres
bahana'ah, and then I'll say, ומאי תקבר מדרבנן, umai tikaveir miderabbanan, why
bury? Because it's rabbinic.
Now, the question is why did we say that? Why don't we
just say it's חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah and we've thought before חולין
בעזרה chullin ba'azarah you bury? So that's a little, it's a little
funny and רש"י Rashi here says, you know, that maybe this would
be of an opinion that חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah at least the
איסור אכילה issur achilah status would not be דאורייתא, de'oraisa, so that's
why it says מדרבנן. miderabbanan.
Maybe if it was a... because it was...
yes, so that's why it stays אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, right? You
wouldn't bury it if it was a נבלה. neveilah. If it was
just a נבלה neveilah you'd feed it to your dog. אסור בהנאה
assur behana'ah and bury is because you're treating it as חולין בעזרה.
chullin ba'azarah. Okay, so it's a little funny. The גמרא Gemara could
have just said this is standard חולין בעזרה. chullin ba'azarah. רש״י Rashi
even says something a little stranger. רש״י Rashi even says that maybe
because you do מליקה melikah and not שחיטה, shechitah, that's not חולין
בעזרה, chullin ba'azarah, which is very strange. If anything, מליקה melikah is
very... makes it very obvious that you're doing a temple-type of a
ritual for this. So the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzes says that the
real point here is it's just a general position about... one minute...
yeah, like I said before, the opinion that חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah
is not דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, at least the איסור אכילה issur achilah is
not דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, the איסור הנאה issur hana'ah is not דאורייתא, d'Oraisa,
and it's saying fine, but at least rabbinically it's אסור בהנאה. assur
behana'ah. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara is saying פשט pshat in our משנה,
mishna, why do you bury it? Is because you found out she
wasn't חייב chayav and it's חולין בעזרה. chullin ba'azarah. Not because of
רב's Rav idea that you found out she was and it wasn't
protected, because we'll assume it would be protected.
Yes, ArtScroll has a footnote to this משנה mishna in תמורה Temurah
that there's a bird חטאת chatas of ספק safek that is burned.
Yeah, so that's in general what you do about חולין בעזרה. chullin
ba'azarah. First of all, no, no, no. First of all, that is
different. That is... that is true. That's when it does not turn
out that you know for sure it's חולין. chullin. This is where
she found out she's not obligated. The normal הלכה halacha is when
she's בספק, besafek, she brings it, she doesn't eat it, and she
burns it. Yeah, that's point number one, which is the... the basic
point, which is that here we're talking about that she found out
she's not and it's definitely חולין בעזרה. chullin ba'azarah. The other point,
by the way, is even with חולין בעזרה, chullin ba'azarah, sometimes you
burn, sometimes you bury, as we learned a day or two ago.
But anyway, moving on. So fine, our משנה mishna is not because
it wasn't watched, our משנה mishna is חולין בעזרה. chullin ba'azarah. So
now the גמרא Gemara goes on. וכי מר דרב, v'chi mar deRav,
so when did רב Rav have to say it atoned? Not in
our משנה. mishna. Our משנה mishna was חולין בעזרה. chullin ba'azarah. On
the previous משנה, mishna, because an earlier משנה mishna we talked about
when the woman after she brought it found out that she was
obligated. על האישה שהביאה חטאתה בספק, al ha'ishah sheheviah chatasoh besafek, this
is a משנה mishna earlier, the woman brought it on doubt, אם
עד שלא נמלקה נודע לה שילדה, im ad shelo nimlekah noda lah
sheyaldah, she found out before she did the מליקה melikah that she
had definitely given birth. ודאי שילדה ודאי תעשה ודאי, vadai sheyaldah vadai
te'aseh vadai, turn it into a חטאת
ודאי, chatas vadai, שמי שהביאה לא נודע מי שילדה נודע, shemi sheheviah
lo noda mi sheyaldah noda, that from the same type of bird
you bring for ספק safek you bring for ודאי. vadai. So if
she found out before the מליקה, melikah, fine, now it's a ודאי.
vadai. Now what was missing from that משנה mishna was a discussion
of what happens if she finds out after the מליקה? melikah? Right,
after the מליקה melikah they brought it, so when they were bringing
it they thought it was a ספק. safek. And now she finds
out, and now it turns out that she's definitely obligated. So can
we just say fine, but I already brought it, it's not a
different קרבן. korban. It's not like an אשם תלוי, asham talui, it's
a חטאת, chatas, I just didn't know. So now I know, so
I was יוצא yotzei with what I brought before. So that's what
רב Rav is talking about. That case wasn't discussed, if she finds
out after the מליקה. melikah. אם משנמלקה נודע שילדה, im mishenimlekah noda
sheyaldah, let's say she finds out after מליקה melikah that she had
given birth, which we hadn't discussed now. On that, אמר רב, amar
Rav, so רב Rav says, מזה דמה, mazzeh damah, you squirt the
blood, ומיצה דמה, umotzeh damah, and you squeeze it out against the
wall of מזבח, mizbe'ach, וכיפרה ומותרת באכילה, v'kipprah umutereth ba'achilah, and it
works, it atones, and she... you can eat it. Sure, why not?
Who cares if when you did the שחיטה shechitah you thought it
was a ספק? safek? It's still the same חטאת העוף. chatas ha'of.
Now you know you're ודאי vadai obligated, go through with it and
you're יוצא yotzei your obligation. Okay, so that's where רב Rav says
וכיפרה v'kipprah when she finds out after מליקה melikah that it is...
that she is definitely obligated. Yes.
But she didn't know what was it considered a תלוי? talui?
No, so that's exactly why it's different. Nobody would say an אשם
תלוי asham talui after שחיטה shechitah could somehow become an אשם ודאי.
asham vadai. But that's because it is a different הלכה halacha of
a קרבן. korban. The Torah has a category called אשם תלוי asham
talui and has a category called אשם ודאי. asham vadai. Here, there's
only one category, חטאת. chatas. So it's not like it has a
different type of a חטאת. chatas. It's just a חטאת, chatas, you
don't happen to know whether you're really obligated in it.
So you
can't be a חטאת מספק. chatas misafek. The one exception is that
we have a tradition for is a woman who's bringing it for
childbirth because if she doesn't bring it she'll never become טהור. tahor.
So normally when it's sin-based you don't, and the only... this is
an exception to that. But it's not a different category of חטאת.
chatas. It's the same חטאת, chatas, you just don't know for sure.
So why shouldn't you now say you were יוצא? yotzei? So that's
what רב Rav says. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says no, אסורה באכילה. asurah ba'achilah. Even though I agree
she was יוצא yotzei her obligation, okay, because yeah, now it turned
out she was obligated, she was יוצא, yotzei, but don't eat it.
Why don't eat it? גזירה שמא יאמרו חטאת העוף הבאה על הספק
נאכלת. gezeirah shema yomru chatas ha'of haba'ah al hasafek ne'echeles. People will
see
that she was bringing it as a ספק, safek, they'll see that
she's eating it, they won't realize you found out in the middle,
so they'll come to think that you can eat a חטאת העוף
chatas ha'of that comes on a ספק. safek. But of course I
agree with it, what... anybody's eating it, it doesn't matter, right, I
said she, whatever, whoever's eating it, the כהן. kohen. Okay, so anyway,
that's why. גזירה. gezeirah. But certainly I agree that it counts as
a חטאת. chatas. I mean, you know, it's not a different category,
it's just you didn't know, now you know. תני לוי כוותיה דרב,
tani Levi k'vasei deRav, לוי Levi taught like רב. Rav. חטאת העוף
הבאה על הספק אם משנמלקה נודע... chatas ha'of haba'ah al hasafek im
mishenimlekah noda...
So if, if it's coming on a doubt, if you find out
after the מליקה melika וילדה ודאי, v'yaldah vadai, מזה דמה, maza dammah,
you do the squirting, ומיצה דמה, u-metzi dammah, you squeeze out the
blood, וכיפרה, v'chipprah, and it atones, ומותרת באכילה. u-mutzeres b'achila. תני כוותיה
דרבי יוחנן, Tani k'vassay d'Rabbi Yochanan, and we taught like Rabbi Yochanan,
that חטאת העוף הבאה על הספק, Chatas ha-of ha-ba'ah al hasafek, אם
עד שלא נמלקה נודע לה שלא ילדה, im ad shelo nimleka noda
lah shelo yaldah,
if before the מליקה, melika, now we're going to deal with both
scenarios, either she found out she didn't give birth or she did.
If she finds out she definitely did not, תצא לחולין, teitzei l'chullin,
then before the מליקה melika it's like the חטאת Chatas that you
find out before the שחיטה shechita whatever, it's totally חולין, chullin, go
back into your regular bird coop or
whatever, או תימכר לחברתה, o timacher l'chavertah, or it's sold to her
friend who needs to bring a bird קרבן. korban. אם עד שלא
נמלקה נודע לה שילדה, im ad shelo nimleka noda lah she-yaldah, if
she knows she definitely, she definitely did not, she definitely gave birth
before the מליקה, melika, then שילדה ודאי תעשה ודאי, she-yaldah vadai ta'aseh
vadai, then bring it as a חטאת ודאי. Chatas vadai. מי שמביא
על לא הודע מביא על הודע, mi she-meivi al lo hoda meivi
al hoda, whether she doesn't know or does know, it's the same
קרבן. korban. So now she can go ahead and go forward now
that she knows she's obligated. Now, what happens if she finds out
after מליקה? melika? אם משנמלקה נודע, im mish'nimleka noda, now it's actually
missing a case, could have had the case of נודע שלא ילדה,
noda shelo yaldah, that was our משנה mishna and then basically it's
תקבר, tikaveir, חולין בעזרה. chullin ba-azarah. If after the מליקה melika it's
נודע שילדה, noda she-yaldah, she did give birth, אסורה אפילו בהנאה, asura
afilu b'hana'ah, she then can't get הנאה hana'ah
from it. Now why? שהעל הספק באה מתחילה כיפר ספיקה והלכה לה.
she-al hasafek ba'ah mit'chila kipper sefeika v'halcha lah. Now the phrase here
is very strange because the phrase here is the phrase we've learned,
we've used by עגלה ערופה egla arufa and אשם תלוי. asham talui.
Where we said the purpose of the עגלה ערופה, egla arufa, the
אשם תלוי asham talui were there to deal with the doubt. Once
they've addressed the state of doubt at that time, the fact that
afterwards it becomes obvious doesn't change their status and they were good
at that time. Here, it is not about atoning for a doubtful
sin, right, here it is about the fact that she needs to
become טהורה. tehora. So it seems like this phrase here is borrowed,
used, doesn't, isn't as sort of literally correct in this case. But
the basic point here is, is that look, it did its job.
It was there, we brought it ספק safek in order to allow
her to become טהורה. tehora. Now we are not going to allow
her to eat it even if she finds out later because again,
that will then go ahead and, you know, and give people misconceptions
and therefore as long as it did the job and it purified
her, we're not going to go so far to let people eat
it, the concern about appearance.
Yes, but the thing is it's very interesting that we're so concerned
about appearances because again, as I was pointing out before, it's only
the כהנים Kohanim that eat it and they only eat it, you
know, they pull things at the end of the day as we
learned. And not only that, we learned that there's so many קינים,
kinim, you know, which is the, you know, the price was so
high. So who's going to know? You know what I mean? They're
going to know that oh this כהן Kohein is eating, oh that's
the one, you know what I mean?
They're all eating the same anyway.
So like, it's a good question.
I hear you. It's a good question. All right, so now we
go on.
Let me, רש"י Rashi by the way, I should say, and maybe
he's influenced by this last line about כיפר ספיקה והלכה לה, kipper
sefeika v'halcha lah, indicates that maybe somehow it still retains its status
of
ספק, safek, which is a little bit what the גמרא Gemara is
indicating, not just מראית העין maris ha-ayin which is what רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said. But since it was שחט shachted when it was
ספק, safek, it still retains its ספק safek status even when you
find out afterwards. And therefore you have to treat it as if
it were, remained a ספק. safek. Not as a דרבנן, d'rabbanan, maybe
sounds even a little more מעיקר הדין. me-ikar ha-din. But anyway, okay,
let's go, sounds a little bit more from the language. Let's go
on now to the next משנה. mishna. המפריש שני סלעים לאשם. Ha-mafrish
shnei sela'im l'asham.
Now, you set aside your two סלעים, sela'im, your two shekels for
the אשם, asham, because we learn out from the תורה Torah it
says כסף שקלים kesef shekalim that it has to be worth two
שקלים. shekalim. ולקח בהן שני אילים לאשם. v'lakach bahen shnei eilim l'asham.
Now you went ahead and you were supposed obviously buy one אשם
asham worth two סלעים. sela'im. What you did is you bought two
rams and you bought them for a סלע sela each. So presumably
you shouldn't be able to use either for your אשם asham because
neither of them is worth two שקלים. shekalim. What then happens? אם
היה אחד מהן יפה שני סלעים, im hayah echad mehen yafeh shnei
sela'im, but one of them either it became worth more after you
bought it or you got a bargain, you got a good deal,
the גמרא Gemara will discuss those, those are different scenarios. In those
types of cases, right now one of the rams is worth two
שקלים. shekalim. So fine, יקרב לאשמו, yikarev l'ashamo, bring it for an
אשם. asham. The תורה Torah is not telling you how much you
have to spend, it's telling you how much it has to be
worth. Like תוספות Tosafos says, if somebody gave you a gift of
the ram, you can't use it because you didn't buy it? No,
it's a question about its how much it's worth, not how much
you paid for it. Okay, so therefore bring the one that's worth
two שקלים. shekalim. Now what do you do with the second one?
It has קדושת אשם kedushas asham but you're not obligated in an
אשם. asham. והשני ירעה עד שיסתאב v'hasheini yireh ad she-yista'eiv and it
gets a מום, mum, וימכר ויפלו דמיו לנדבה. v'yimacher v'yip'lu damav l'nedava.
Use the money for an עולה olah because the הלכה halacha is
מותר אשם mosar asham is brought as an עולה. olah. Right, a
חטאת, Chatas, the basic rule is that it has to die if
you can't do it or whatever, but for an אשם, asham, if
you can't bring an אשם, asham, then the money goes toward, you
redeem it and the money goes toward an עולה. olah.
I can't keep it until it's worth two סלעים sela'im and then
use it for?
You could, but you have two, you're only חייב chayav one. Oh,
just for the next time I see. So that's an interesting point.
Or you're already less, or for someone else.
And maybe for רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, right, you know, again, you
can't really switch a...
We explicitly said the assumption is the same way you can't use
a חטאת chatas from one sin to the next, you can't use
an אשם תלוי asham talui from one sin to the next.
I'm not trying to remember the גמרא Gemara had some discussion similar
to that before. I'm trying to remember if we sort of explicitly
said that, but anyway my assumption would be that you cannot- once
it's designated for a particular sin it can't be reapplied. לוקח בהם
שני אילים וכולי. Loke'ach bahem shenei eilim vechulei. Now what you did
is you had sanctified this money, rather than buy two rams to
be an אשם, asham, you went and you bought two rams just
for your own purposes to use in your flock. Now how were
you allowed to do that? The answer is you weren't allowed to
do that. You stole the money from הקדש, hekdesh, you were חייב
מעילה. chayav me'ilah. And now we're going to start, it's sort of
like a segue into the next מסכת, masechet, we're going to start
talking about bringing a קרבן korban for מעילה. me'ilah. What do you
do if you sin with מעילה? me'ilah? You bring an אשם מעילות.
asham me'ilos. How much does that- you give back the money in
a fifth, plus you bring an אשם מעילות. asham me'ilos. How much
does that אשם asham have to be worth? Two שקל. shekel. So
there's a little bit of like we're going to do a little
sort of, you know, becomes sort of infinite loop type thing, not
exactly.
But anyway, you went ahead and used it for חולין, chullin, it's
still מעילה. me'ilah.
In other words, you did use it. You went to the marketplace,
you bought two rams, and you did it with the intention of
keeping them for yourself, not of transferring the קדושה. kedushah.
But I can't just go then and now transfer? Meaning I just-
I'm taking them home and you
paid the money, paid the money that was sanctified, and you paid
it as if it was your own, and you paid it for
a purchase of your own. You're not doing it as an act
of פדיון. pidyon. The right- it's the same money switching hands, but
it's how you frame it. A lot of things are how you
frame them. Okay? Are you- are you giving a woman a gift
or are you מקדש mekadesh her? It's all the same thing you're
giving her, right? It's a question of how you frame it. All
right. So חולין, chullin, you took- put them to be your own.
אחד יפה שני סלעים ואחד יפה עשרה זוז. Echad yafeh shenei sela'im
ve'echad yafeh asarah zuz. Now one of them is worth two סלע,
sela, one of them is worth ten זוז. zuz. A זוז zuz
is four סלע- sela no, a סלע sela is four זוז. zuz.
So this is actually worth not eight זוז, zuz, which is two
סלעים, sela'im, but actually more, it's worth ten זוז. zuz. You got
a real bargain for your two שקל, shekel, you got two rams
that were worth more than four שקל. shekel. But okay. Now the
purpose of saying ten זוז zuz is the following: is that when-
by- when you do מעילה me'ilah you have to give back the
amount plus a חומש. chomesh. Now a חומש chomesh is a fifth
after you give it back, which is really a quarter of the
base. So what is- what would that be? If you- if what
you stole was two שקל, shekel, שמונה זוז, shmonah zuz, then that
plus a חומש, chomesh, this is ten, right? Because now the extra
two you gave is a fifth of ten. Okay, so here's the
question though. When I steal from the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, if
I stole from בדק הבית, bedek habayis, I give the money back
to בדק הבית. bedek habayis. Let's say I stole from money that
was designated as a קרבן. korban. How do I give it back?
So I give it back by bringing a קרבן korban with the
money I give back. But what about the extra חומש? chomesh? Well,
that I can also include in the giving back. So if I
stole two- two שקל shekel that were designated for an אשם, asham,
my אשם asham for my previous sin, right, my אשם תלוי asham
talui or whatever my original אשם asham was, אשם ודאי asham vadai
doesn't matter, I stole two שקל. shekel. Now I have to give
back ten זוז, zuz, two שקל shekel plus two point whatever it
is, two point four שקל, shekel, okay, I have to give that
back. I give it back towards the same function, towards being brought
as that original אשם. asham. So the ten זוז zuz ram is
now going to be brought as the original אשם. asham. Now I-
because I have two rams here, might as well use them for
my obligations, so the ten זוז zuz one goes for the original
קרבן. korban. The- the שמונה זוז shmonah zuz one, the two שקל
shekel one, might as well use that for my- for my אשם
asham that I'm חייב chayav for אשם מעילות asham me'ilos because I
now did another sin that's חייב chayav an אשם, asham, I did
מעילה. me'ilah. So that goes towards my אשם מעילות. asham me'ilos. Is
that clear? So I started with a חיוב chiyuv of an אשם.
asham. I stole from that. I give- give back plus twenty percent
or twenty-five percent or whatever, right? That's now give back a more
expensive אשם. asham. And because I did that act of stealing and
מעילה, me'ilah, I have to bring an אשם מעילות asham me'ilos and
I bring another ram worth two שקל. shekel. Just so happens I
have both of those rams available to me because that's what I
bought with the money I stole. Okay, but obviously even if you
didn't buy it with the money you stole, that would be what
you would have to do, we're just creating a scenario where you
can use what you bought. Okay. אם היה אחד יפה שני סלעים
ואחד יפה
עשרה זוז. Im hayah echad yafeh shenei sela'im ve'echad yafeh asarah zuz.
So where were we? אחד יפה שני סלעים ואחד יפה עשרה זוז.
Echad yafeh shenei sela'im ve'echad yafeh asarah zuz. So what do you
do? היפה שני סלעים יקרב לאשמו, Hayafah shenei sela'im yikarev le'ashamo, which
he means for your אשם מעילות, asham me'ilos, for your אשם asham
for bringing for the act of מעילה. me'ilah. והשני, Vehasheni, the one
worth the שמונה זוז shmonah zuz plus twenty percent, not שמונה זוז,
shmonah zuz, the two שקל shekel plus twenty percent, the ten זוז,
zuz, למעילתו. leme'ilato. That you do for your payback for your מעילה
me'ilah money and you bring it- how do you pay it back?
You pay it back by bringing now your original אשם asham with
a- that's now worth more money. Okay, now אחד לאשם ואחד לחולין.
Echad le'asham ve'echad lechullin. Let's say you used this money that you
stole, or you didn't steal, you stole half of it. So you
took- set aside two שקל. shekel. One שקל shekel you used to
buy an אשם asham with, an animal that would be your קרבן.
korban. Fine, then you- no problem with that, you did what you
were supposed to. The other you stole and you brought an animal
for your own flock. Okay, you could actually imagine a scenario like
that. The guy takes the two שקל shekel to the store to
buy a קרבן korban and then he finds a קרבן korban that's
worth two שקל shekel that- that's being sold for one. So he
says great, I'll pay one. And now look, I have an extra
שקל, shekel, I might as well buy something for myself, okay? So
there's a scenario that one you did use properly and one you
did not. Now, so you still did מעילה, meilah, right? So what
are you going to do? So, אם היה של אשם יפה שתי
סלעים יקרב לאשמו. im hayah shel asham yafeh shtei sela'im yikarev le'ashamo.
If the one that you spent the one שקל shekel on as
an אשם asham was worth two, you got a bargain, so fine,
you could bring it as an אשם. asham. An אשם asham has
to be worth two. So that you bring as an אשם. asham.
But now what have you done? You did מעילה meilah on one
שקל. shekel. So you have to give back that שקל shekel plus
20% and you have to bring an אשם מעילות, asham meilot, okay?
והשני למעילתו. vehashani limeilato. The second ram you bought, here the word
מעילה meilah means the opposite of what it meant before, the גמרא
Gemara will deal with that. The second ram you bought counts for
your אשם מעילות, asham meilot, okay? Bring that assuming that that's also
worth two שקל. shekel. I'm sorry,
yeah, that counts as your אשם מעילות asham meilot assuming that that's
worth two שקל. shekel. And now you have to give back the
money that you stole plus 20%. ויביא עמה סלע וחומשה. veyavi imah
sela vechumshah.
And now, and now you also have to give back the money
you stole plus 20% or 25% and then you give that back
separately. So the one you brought for your first אשם, asham, you
did good, bye, bring that assuming it's worth sufficient amount of money.
The second one, if it's also worth two שקל, shekel, might as
well use that for your אשם מעילות. asham meilot. And now you
still have to go give back the money you stole plus 20%.
Okay. Now of course in this case, what would you do with
the money? Because I said you give it back for the same
purpose, but you're not giving it back for an אשם, asham, you
already brought your אשם. asham. So since the הלכה halacha is that
an אשם asham you can't use, the money becomes an עולה, olah,
right? If you were to redeem an אשם asham you couldn't use,
the money becomes an עולה. olah. So this money you're giving back
having stolen אשם asham money now gets used for bringing an עולה.
olah. Yes. Is מעילה meilah like let's say I just go and
I just buy two animals, I don't think anything, חולין chullin or
אשם, asham, is that מעילה? meilah? Meaning is it מעילה meilah if
I don't specifically think it's for הקדש hekdesh or is מעילה meilah
when I...
We'll discuss that when we get to מעילה. Meilah. So we have
a whole מסכת masechet about it. Okay, let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. מאי מעילתו דקתני? mai meilato diktani? Now, רישא, reisha,
והשני למעילתו. vehashani limeilato. So now the problem is as we're going
to point out that the words מעילה meilah mean different things in
two halves of the משנה. Mishnah. The first part where it says
that the ram that's worth ten זוז zuz I use for my
מעילה, meilah, what does that mean I use for my מעילה? meilah?
אילימא אל אשם, eilima el asham, if it means the
אשם מעילות, asham meilot, that's what I'm using it for, למימר דחומש
בהדי איל מייתי ליה. lemeimar dechomesh bahadi ayil mayisei lei. It sounds
like you're adding your 20% for your אשם מעילות. asham meilot. Now
this is going to get again because the language is reversed, it
gets confusing. But again the point is the משנה Mishnah said you
use the ten זוז, zuz, which is what you stole plus 20%
for your מעילה. meilah. So that word מעילה meilah can mean one
of two things. It could mean for your אשם מעילות asham meilot
or it could mean for your payback money, which is going to
go towards your first אשם. asham. So if it means for your
אשם מעילות, asham meilot, then that sounds like the extra fifth you
give, because this is the one with an extra 20%, can be
used towards the אשם מעילות, asham meilah, okay? And that's not normally
the assumption. Normally the assumption is the extra 20% you give goes
with the base that you gave towards the function that it was
stolen from. Right, is that clear? Yes? Right? I steal, let's assume
it's בדק הבית. bedek habayit. I steal from בדק הבית bedek habayit
$100. I give back $125 all to בדק הבית bedek habayit and
then I bring my אשם. asham. It's not like I give back
$100 to בדק הבית bedek habayit and I use now the extra
$25 to make a nicer אשם. asham. Okay, so here when it
says you give the ten זוז, zuz, the thing plus the 25%
for your מעילה, meilah,
the גמרא Gemara is going to say it can't mean for your
אשם מעילות asham meilah because the extra money doesn't go towards your
אשם, asham, it goes towards the thing you stole it from. Okay.
So if אילימא בהדי גזילה, eilima bahadi gezeilah, one minute,
אילימא איל אשם eilima ayil asham that you add the 20% to
your ram, אלמא דחומש בהדי איל מייתי ליה? alma dechomesh bahadi ayil
mayisei lei? That sounds like you're adding your חומש chomesh to the
קרבן. korban. והא כתיב ואת אשר חטא מן הקדש ישלם ואת חמישיתו
יוסף עליו, veha ketiv ve'et asher chata min hakodesh yeshalem ve'et chamishito
yosef alav, that you pay back what you stole plus 20%, which
means that you pay it back all together to the same source,
to whatever purpose it was taken from. אלמא בהדי גזילה מייתי ליה,
alma bahadi gezeilah mayisei lei, you bring it back with what you
stole. ועוד קתני, ve'od katani, and yet the סיפא, seifa, the end
of the משנה Mishnah says, אחד אשם ואחד חולין, echad asham ve'echad
chullin, when you did one for an אשם asham and one for
חולין. chullin. אם היה של אשם יפה שתי סלעים יקרב לאשמו והשני
למעילתו. im hayah shel asham yafeh shtei sela'im yikarev le'ashamo vehashani limeilato.
It gives the case where you use the two rams, one for
your first אשם, asham, the other for your אשם מעילות. asham meilah.
And then it says what do you do with the money you
stole? ויביא עמה סלע וחומשה. veyavi imah sela vechumshah. You pay back
your שקל shekel plus 20%. So there in the end it's clear
that the base plus the 20%, the principal plus the 20% is
all paid back together. So when you are going to now bring
a ram of ten זוז, zuz, which is the base plus 20%,
it's not for your אשם מעילות, asham meilah, it's for your payback.
So your payback is what you stole it from, your first
אשם. asham. אלמא חומש בהדי גזילה מייתי ליה. alma chomesh bahadi gezeilah
mayisei lei. You see you bring the 20% with what you stole.
אלא מעילתו מאי? ela meilato mai? So what does מעילתו meilato mean
when you bring the ram of the ten זוז? zuz? It means
מאי דאשתני מהקדש, mai de'ishtani mehekdesh, that meaning what you pay for
your מעילה, meilah, meaning you pay it back as what you stole,
you pay it back for your payback. וישנו
אתנו, veyeshno esno, they take out the word וישנו. veyeshno. What is
it? דשני מהקדש דשני בשני סלעים דאפרשינו לאשם. deshani me'hekdesh deshani bishnei
sela'im d'afrishinu l'asham. דשני deshani I don't know. Anyway, whatever. וישנו veyeshno
is a little strange word. Anyway, משני סלעים
דאפרשינו
לאשם. mishnei sela'im d'afrishinu l'asham. You pay it back for the two
סלע sela that you stole from for your original אשם. asham. ולקח
בהן שני אילים לחולין velakach bahen shenei eilim l'chullin and with that
money you use that money to buy two rams for secular purposes.
דיפה שתי סלעים מקריב ליה אל אשם, deyafeh shtei sela'im makriv lei
el asham, the one worth two shekel you bring for your קרבן
מעילות, korban meilos, ויפה עשרה זוז veyafeh asarah zuz and the one
that's worth ten זוז, zuz, which is your two shekel plus twenty
percent, יהיב ליה למאי דאיתהני מהקדש yahiv lei l'mai d'is'hani me'hekdesh you
give it back for where how you from where you stole it
from, where you benefited. You benefited because you took it away as
אשם asham number one money, right? And therefore you give back that
plus twenty percent for אשם asham number one. והוי ליה גזילו וחומשו,
vehavah lei gezeilo v'chumsho, which is what you stole for plus twenty
percent. ומאי מעילתו, umai meiloso, what does it mean that you give
for your מעילה? meilah? גזילו. gezeilo. When you're paying back what you
stole, the ten זוז zuz now in the form of a ram
is being paid back for your מעילה, meilah, meaning what you stole.
Okay. So now again, see the language is a little redundant, but
okay. Anyway, the basic point here is that when it says you
stole from your אשם asham money, when you give back plus twenty
percent, you're giving back to where you stole from, to the original
אשם, asham, and then your the אשם asham that you bring is
separate and that's the base two for אשם מעילה, asham meilah, that's
the base two. Here you're giving back plus twenty percent because that's
where you stole from. So the word מעילתו meiloso in the רישא,
reisha, when it says the ten זוז zuz goes for the מעילה,
meilah, means the ten זוז zuz go for payback from what you
stole. The problem is at the end of the משנה mishnah it
means the opposite, it means something else. So let's take a look.
במאי אוקימתא למעילתו, bemai okimta l'meiloso,
what do we say the word מעילה meilah means to the רישא?
reisha? גזילו. gezeilo. When you're paying back what you stole, then you
pay back the ten זוז zuz in the form of a ram
because you stole from from אשם asham money. אימא סיפא, eima seifa,
look at the end. אחד אשם ואחד וכולי, echad asham v'echad v'chulei,
you brought one for an אשם asham and one for חולין. chullin.
אם היה של אשם יפה שתי סלעים, im hayah shel asham yafeh
shtei sela'im, if the one you brought for an אשם asham is
worth two סלע, sela, יקרב לאשמו, yikrav l'ashamo, bring that for your
original אשם. asham. That's
good. והשני למעילה, vehasheini l'meilah, the second ram, here the word מעילה
meilah doesn't mean payback because here the word for מעילה meilah means
it's coming for your קרבן, korban, for your אשם מעילות. asham meilos.
ויביא עמו סלע וחומשו, veyavi immo sela v'chumsho,
and then that's the payback, the shekel plus the twenty percent. So
here the word מעילה meilah doesn't mean payback, here the word מעילה
meilah means your אשם מעילות. asham meilos. אמר מעילתו אל אשם, amar
meiloso el asham, means your אשם מעילות. asham meilos. רישא קרי ליה
למעילתו גזילו, reisha kari lei l'meiloso gezeilo, in the beginning, top of
כז עמוד א, kaf zayin amud aleph, you the word מעילה meilah
means your the money you stole and what you're paying back. סיפא
קרי ליה למעילתו אל אשם, seifa kari lei l'meiloso el asham, and
at the end you're calling the word מעילה meilah to refer to
your אשם מעילות. asham meilos. So the גמרא gemara says yes. רישא
דהוי ליה איל דזבן, reisha d'havah lei ayil d'zavan, they switch word
רובן ruban here to דזבן. d'zavan. דזבנינא? d'zavinna? Okay, we'll just go
with that. Right. So the ram דזבן, d'zavan, the ram that you
bought, קרן וחומש, keren v'chumsh, since actually there the ram was your
the full payback, it was the ten זוז zuz and the payback,
so you could call that ram the מעילה meilah because it actually
was the payback. קרי ליה למעילתו גזילו. kari lei l'meiloso gezeilo. So
yeah, we'll call it the מעילה meilah because that represents the payback.
סיפא דלא הוי ליה איל דזבן קרן וחומש, seifa d'lo havah lei
ayil d'zavan keren v'chomesh, in the end where you don't have the
idea of an actual animal being brought represents the payback, קרי אל
אשם מעילתו, kari el asham meiloso, so it calls the אל אשם
el asham the word מעילה, meilah, which sounds to be like, so
still so so why are you being inconsistent? It sounds like the
answer is we'll use the phrase מעילתו meiloso to refer to a
קרבן. korban. So when it can refer to the when what your
payback is taking the form of a קרבן, korban, then we will
call that מעילתו. meiloso. When your payback isn't taking the form of
a קרבן, korban, we'll use the word מעילה meilah to refer to
your
אשם מעילות. asham meilos. Okay. Anyway, ויביא עמו סלע וחומשו. veyavi immo
sela v'chumsho. Okay, so that was as if it weren't complicated enough,
that just complicated because the word מעילה meilah means different things. But
the basic principle is clear, which is you you you give back
the money plus twenty percent. That twenty percent does not go to
other קרבן korban obligations or to your even your אשם מעילות. asham
meilos. That twenty percent goes back or twenty-five percent really goes back
to the place you took it from. If the place you took
it from is a קרבן, korban, then it means now you give
it as a nicer קרבן. korban. If the קרבן korban was already
brought, then you like true however then it would be worked as
leftover money from a קרבן, korban, so in this case it would
turn into an עולה. olah. But the twenty percent goes back to
the place you took it from plus now you bring an אשם
מעילות. asham meilos. Okay. This is a very good transition into next
מסכת. masechet. Now the גמרא gemara says like this. בעי רב מנשיא
בר גדא. ba'ei Rav Menashya bar Gada. So בקינוס חומשין מהו? bekinnus
chumshin mahu? So he asks the following question. Let's say you collect
a lot of fifths. מהו שיתכפר? mahu sheyitkaper? Can you bring that
as your complete קרבן? korban? So what's the scenario? So the scenario
is let's say you I go ahead and I, here I'll give
you the שיטה מקובצת's Shita Mekubetzet way of understanding this. Here I
had one שקל Shekel that was belonged to הקדש, Hekdesh, okay, and
that was set aside, I don't know, for my, for my אשם,
Asham, my, whatever it was, for my אשם תלוי Asham Talui or
whatever, one שקל. Shekel. I got benefit from it, and so now
I have to pay back a, you know, a שקל Shekel plus
a fifth. And I got benefit from it again and again and
again and again. Now of course the question is why again and
again? Once you got benefit from it once, it goes out לחולין.
l'chullin. There are times when it goes out לחולין, l'chullin, times it
doesn't go out לחולין. l'chullin. Anyway, the point is, I benefited from
it four times. So now the, it's a little ironic, the four
fifths, because the fifth is really a quarter, the four times all
wind up now being worth a שקל. Shekel. Can I take that
שקל Shekel that is a fifth and use that towards
my actual קרבן Korban that I have to bring as my obligation?
So, so you understand the scenario? Meaning normally the case would be
that I stole something which was worth two, I pay back 2.4
or whatever, 2.5. 2.5,
okay, I pay back 2.5,
and now that's brought as my קרבן. Korban. But fine, but that
type of case part of the money, the basic cost of the
קרבן Korban was paid for with my own money, not with the
extra fifth. What happens in a scenario where I'm חייב chayav multiple
fifths, let's not worry about the details, and now the money I'm
using to bring a קרבן, Korban, even part of the base cost,
maybe the entire base cost, but at least part of the base
cost is coming from that fifth. Am I allowed, now I'm doing
the right thing with the fifth, I'm giving it back as it
were to the place I took it from, right? I took it
from the אשם, Asham, I'm giving it back to the אשם. Asham.
Okay, but even though I'm doing the right thing, can I use
it to get atonement for, to help me get, you know, satisfy
my obligation? Right, you understand the difference of the previous case, right?
No, no, the previous case is I stole something worth two, I
gave back 2.5, but the extra fifth wasn't helping me gain my
atonement, the two would have sufficed to purchase something worth two to
gain my atonement, the extra fifth just made it a fatter animal.
Here, because I stole, let's say I stole, I don't know, 1.8
or something, and now because of the additional fifth, that's an easier
way of giving you the example, because of the additional fifth, I'm
able to afford the right size קרבן, Korban, right? So for my
earlier sin or my אשם תלוי, Asham Talui, whatever it is, can
I use a חומש chomesh to not only as payback but to
help me satisfy to gain atonement for some other thing, okay, for
something that I was obligated to bring a קרבן Korban for?
Right, as opposed to giving it to the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
right?
What was it? Or as opposed to, no, spending the entire, making
sure that two, the entire two שקל Shekel were from my own
pocket and that the fifth was on top of that and made
it a fatter קרבן Korban but was not part of the base
cost. Okay, that's the question. אם תמצא לומר, Im timtzo lomar, now
this ties into a general question. The question is, can you gain
atonement through שבח הקדש? shevach hekdesh? Something that was
sanctified and was a benefit, it sort of like increased value. And
this is being treated as a type of שבח הקדש. shevach hekdesh.
Normal שבח הקדש shevach hekdesh is I buy an animal and it
gets fatter. Okay, and before it wasn't worth enough as a קרבן,
Korban, now it is worth enough, but it got fatter once it
was הקדש. hekdesh. Can I use that to make it a valuable
enough קרבן Korban to work for me? Okay, but here it's שבח
הקדש shevach hekdesh because הקדש hekdesh had an amount and because I
stole from it and now I paid back, the interest was something
that הקדש hekdesh increased in its value because of the הלכה halacha
of מעילה. me'ilah. So can I use that? That's the
question. מהו? Mahu? מהו שיתכפר? Mahu sheyitkaper? מי אמרינן, Mi amrinan, do
we say אם תמצא לומר אדם מתכפר בשבח הקדש, im timtzo lomar
adam mitkaper b'shevach hekdesh, even if normally you say a person can
be atoned for, like he bought an animal for one שקל Shekel
and אשם Asham and then it got fatter and became worth two
and it became the, so even after it's הקדש hekdesh it got,
it went up to the minimum
value, so משום דקטרח קמיה, mishum d'kata'ach kamei, that's because maybe he
put an effort to feed it and other types of things, right,
that increased its value, so it's not all happening automatically. אבל הכא
דלא טרח, Aval hacha d'lo tara, קטרח kata'ach here it's increased in
value did not happen because you invested in it, it's because you
stole, so you have to just put money out of your pocket,
לא מתכפר, lo mitkaper, maybe it's not really seen, meaning the way
I would conceptualize this is it's not really seen as a, you
know, as a natural extension and growth of the original thing and
therefore you cannot gain atonement with that, only from the original קדושה.
kedusha. או דילמא, O dilma, or do we say אם תמצא לומר
אין אדם מתכפר בשבח הקדש, im timtzo lomar ein adam mitkaper b'shevach
hekdesh, even if you go the opposite way and normally you cannot
use the fact that the animal got fatter to satisfy its minimum
value, משום דלא אפרשיה, mishum d'lo afrishei, because then when you set
aside the animal originally and sanctified it, it wasn't worth the right
amount. אבל הני כינוס חומשין, Aval hane kinus chumshin, but this, once
you added your 20% and you gathered up multiple 20%s, דאפרשיה, d'afrishei,
and then you sanctified it directly for the use of a קרבן.
Korban. So on the one hand it's not a natural growth from
the thing you sanctified, on the other hand you sanctified this directly
for this purpose. Okay, איכא למימר מתכפר, ikka l'meimar mitkaper, maybe that
would work. And now, without really answering that, we're just going to
turn to the general question of, so that's the question: Do you
look at the money you pay back from מעילה me'ilah as שבח
הקדש shevach hekdesh or not? But now we're going to go to
the more general question of is can you gain atonement with שבח
הקדש. shevach hekdesh. איבעי להו, Iba'ei lehu, they raised the question. מתכפר
אדם בשבח הקדש או לא? Mitkaper adam b'shevach hekdesh o lo? תא
שמע, Ta shema, so this is a case where the animal gets
fatter. Now we're going to look at our משנה Mishnah because our
משנה Mishnah says you spent one שקל shekel and it's worth two.
So we're going to assume that that's a case where it got
fatter after you bought it and שבח הקדש shevach hekdesh
is being a discount.
Exactly. But let's take a look. תא שמע. Ta shema. המפריש שני
סלעים לאשם, Hamiafrish shenei sela'im l'asham, you set aside two. ולקח בהן
שני אילים לאשם, V'lakach bahen shenei eilim l'asham, with your two you
brought two, you brought two rams for an אשם. asham. האי אחד
מהן יפה בשני סלעים Hai echad mehen yafeh b'shenei sela'im and one
that you brought for one סלע sela is really worth two. יקרב
לאשמו, Yikarev l'ashamo, you can bring it for your אשם. asham. והשני
ירעה עד שיסתאב וימכר ויפלו דמיו לנדבה V'hasheni yira'eh ad sheyista'ev v'yimacher
v'yipelu damav l'nedavah and the second one you wait for a מום
mum and then the money goes for an עולה. olah. Fine. מאי
לאו, Mai lav, so how is it that one here you paid
one and it's worth two? מאי לאו דזבין בארבעה
זוזי, Mai lav d'zavin b'arba'ah zuzei, that is, meaning for זוז, zuz,
איהו ושבח דשוי תמניא ihu v'shavach d'shavei tamnya and then it became
fatter and more valuable and now it's worth eight? So now it's
only worth the minimum value because it improved after you bought it.
So you see you're מתכפר בשבח הקדש. mitkaper b'shevach hekdesh.
שמע מינה אדם מתכפר בשבח הקדש, Shema mina adam mitkaper b'shevach hekdesh,
you see you can be atoned with the amount that it improved.
לא, Lo, no. הכא במאי עסקינן דאוזיל רועה גביה Hacha b'mai askinan
d'ozil ro'eh gabei that the shepherd gave you a discount, okay, and
therefore you got a bargain. And that's why it works because at
the end of the day, as I said before, it's not how
much you spend, it's how much it's worth. So you, so therefore
when it was originally sanctified, it was worth the two שקל shekel
even though you only spent one, but it is not an increase
in value that happened after it was sanctified.
תא שמע, Ta shema, come in here. לקח איל בסלע. Lakach ayil
b'sela. Here's an explicit תוספתא. Tosefta. You bought a ram with one
שקל. shekel. ופיטמו U'pitmo and you fattened it. והעמידו על שתיים V'he'emido
al shtayim and now it's worth two שקל. shekel. כשר, Kasher, it
works, it satisfies your minimum value. So that's explicit, it improved after
you bought it and sanctified it. שמע מינה אדם מתכפר בשבח הקדש,
Shema mina adam mitkaper b'shevach hekdesh, you see that it works, you
can get your atonement through the increase. לא, Lo, פיטמו שאני, pitmo
shani, when you actually fattened it, that's different. You invested your money
into getting it to be worth more. That is like your own
money went towards it, it's not like it happened by itself. דחסריה
תמניא, D'chasrei tamnya, we're assuming that the reason it improved to be
worth four זוז zuz more, one שקל shekel more, is because you
invested one זוז, zuz, one שקל shekel more. So you actually there,
actually your investment was two שקל, shekel, it did not happen by
itself. תא שמע, Ta shema, like my myself example. You know, it
just grazes and grows, whatever, exactly. Or that your investment, you know,
hopefully if it's a smart investment, then it increases in value more
than the amount you invested. So that amount that goes beyond what
you invested is still שבח הקדש, shevach hekdesh, it's not directly what
you invested. תא שמע, Ta shema, so that's where the גמרא Gemara
is going. לקח איל בסלע והרי הוא בשתיים, Lakach ayil b'sela v'harei
hu b'shtayim, this is the continuation of the תוספתא. Tosefta. You bought
it for one and behold it's worth two. So behold it's worth
two sounds like it happened afterwards and it just increased in value
by itself. כשר, Kasher, it works. ומשני התם נמי כשפיטמו. U'mishni hatam
nami k'shepitmo. No, we're talking that you fattened it. אי הכי היינו
רישא? Ei hachi hainu reisha? That's the first case, because this is
all part of the same
תוספתא. Tosefta. No. רישא דזבין בארבעה ואשכחיה בארבעה אחרינא דחסריה תמניא. Reisha
d'zavin b'arba'ah v'ashkachei b'arba'ah achrina d'chasrei tamnya. The first case is you
bought it for four זוז, zuz, you invested four more and now
it's worth eight. And at the end of the day, you paid
eight זוז zuz out of your own pocket. So there it's not
הקדש's hekdesh improvement, it's your own investment of eight. סיפא דזבין איל
בארבעה ואשכחיה בתלתא ושוי תמניא. Seifa d'zavin ayil b'arba'ah v'ashkachei b'tlata v'shavei
tamnya. The end case, you only invested three זוז zuz in this
animal, but you made a profit, it's increase in value went up
to be four זוז, zuz, so now it's worth a total of
eight. So that type of a case, the גמרא Gemara is saying
it's still not שבח הקדש. shevach hekdesh. Of course the problem is,
as the גמרא Gemara is going to later say, it is שבח
הקדש, shevach hekdesh, the extra one is שבח הקדש shevach hekdesh and
that's still working for you. So the גמרא Gemara is going to
come around to that. But for now we're trying to say that
it's not necessarily a normal case of by itself, you invested. אי
הכי, Ei hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara, if that's true, אימא סיפא,
eima seifa, look at the very end of the תוספתא. Tosefta. וישלים
סלע. V'yashlim sela.
The end of the תוספתא Tosefta says now that it's worth two,
fine, you can bring it as a קרבן, korban, but you should
still pay a סלע, sela, a שקל, shekel, because you saved yourself
a שקל. shekel. Now, what does that sense does that make? I
mean, well, why are you paying a שקל? shekel? What did you
do wrong? It's now a minimum value anyway. But it also sounds
like you didn't invest anything. It sounds like you got off, you
know, a שקל shekel and therefore you're paying a שקל. shekel. So
the גמרא Gemara says דחסריה זוזא. d'chasrei zuza. So you, what do
you mean you pay a full סלע? sela? You spent seven זוז,
zuz, seven-eighths of a שקל, shekel, you know, seven זוז, zuz, so
why should you have to pay a full שקל? shekel? You didn't
even, you know, you didn't even get a benefit of a full
שקל. shekel. No. מאי ישלים תשלומי דסלע. Mai yashlim tashlumei d'sela. Okay,
don't pay a full סלע, sela, pay the remnant of the סלע,
sela, pay the extra זוז. zuz. So this is a weird תוספתא
Tosefta we're going to have to figure out anyway, and a weird
הלכה, halakhah, why is it that if you, what if it improved
and now it's worth two שקל shekel and you can bring it,
you still... Why do you have to pay הקדש Hekdesh the money
that you saved? Why should that be responsibility? You brought a requisite
ram. But anyway, but the fact that it says a סלע selah
makes it sound like you saved a full סלע, selah, and it
sounds like it's all שבח הקדש, shevach Hekdesh, and say no, maybe
you only saved a little bit. Okay, let's, but that's what you
pay back. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Let's keep
on going. The
גמרא Gemara says, תא שמע תניא דאיצטריך ליה tasha shema tanya de'itzlei
דאין אדם מתכפר בשבח הקדש, de'ein adam miskaper beshevach Hekdesh, but wait
a minute, if you cannot use the הקדש's Hekdesh improvements, כי האי
תשלום דסלע מאי הוי? ki hai tashlum deselah mai havei? So how
would you read it? You're paying what you saved. So what would
you say the logic is you're paying what you saved? Well, maybe
because you can't benefit from במתכפר בשבח הקדש, be miskaper beshevach Hekdesh,
so you have to pay it. But it's not a que, but
but in the end, the money I'm paying isn't part of the
קרבן. korban. So if the problem is I can't use that to
satisfy the minimum cost of a קרבן, korban, right, as part of
my atonement, how does it help to pay that difference? מאי הוי,
Mai havei, what are you helping? היה בעי שתי סלעים, Haya be'ei
shtei selayim, and it has to be worth two. And if it's
only considered worth what you invested, it's not worth, you didn't invest
two. וליכא. Veleka. So לעולם קסבר le'olam kasavar you're right. This תוספתא
Tosefta makes it clear אדם מתכפר בשבח הקדש, adam miskaper beshevach Hekdesh,
that you can use for your קרבן korban the amount it improved
even beyond what you invested, and maybe that's a whole סלע selah
or even in the scenario we gave it's a זוז. zuz. It
invested, it improved somewhat beyond what you invested, and that works. And
the קרבן korban actually works even if you don't give any money.
Obviously, because how does giving money help to make the קרבן korban
work? So what's the point of giving money? אי הכי תשלום דסלע
לא ייתן, Ie hachi tashlum deselah lo yiten, why are you giving
the the extra amount that you bet that you saved? היינו טעמא
דקא יהיב תשלום דסלע, Hainu ta'ama deka ya'iv tashlum deselah, here's why
it's a separate reason. גזירה שמא יאמרו היה פחות משתי סלעים מכפר.
Gezeira shema yomru haya pachot mishtei selayim mechaper.
People will know you only pay the סלע. selah. They won't be
aware, maybe they'll know also what you invested, again this is like
Michael's case, how all of a sudden is everybody aware of all
your business? But anyway, and therefore we don't want people to think,
oh, I heard this guy, that'll definitely happen because you always have
to tell people about the bargains you got. Oh, I heard this
guy was able to bring a an אשם asham and he only
had to spend a שקל shekel and a שקל shekel and a
half. A שקל shekel he bought, a half he invested, but he
didn't have to spend two שקל. shekel. I'll next time I'll also
buy one only for a שקל shekel and a half. So therefore
we're going to make sure that you spend two שקל. shekel. Okay,
so even though, but that's just to be concerned about the impression
it's creating with other people. על פי הלכה, Al pi halakha, even
if you bought it, it was worth less and it improved by
itself, again it's not how much you spend really, it's how much
it was worth, but even when it was worth and you sanctified
it was worth less than two and it improved by itself, that
also can count towards the minimum value.
I understand, but but if I buy it for one, then I
feed it another one's worth. Right. And that's okay according to everybody
or not?
Yeah. But but that certainly is okay. But in the end we're
saying you don't even need that. Even if it completely improved by
itself, we are saying אדם מתכפר בשבח הקדש. adam miskaper beshevach Hekdesh.
People are going to say, oh look, I saw he bought this
really scrawny animal, it wasn't worth.
No, no, no, no, no. In that case you were, oh, if
you invested then you would not say because then in the end
you wouldn't say that I had to spend less than two שקל
shekel for it. Okay, so we're not concerned about the impression. But
if you actually didn't spend out of pocket, we're going to make
sure because of creating bad impressions or whatever, misleading people, that you're
going to have to spend two שקל shekel out of pocket, whether
into the קרבן korban or to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash coffers,
you're going to have to put that money out of pocket. But
regardless, the fact that that's only a rabbinic thing. The fact that
it improved by itself, that can be used for a קרבן. korban.
Okay, let's keep on going.
Okay, עיקר דין ikkar din is
yes, yes, yes, yes, אדם מתכפר. adam miskaper. מאי הוי עלה,
Mai
havei
alah, what was the upshot? I mean yes, it sounds like we're
saying אדם מתכפר בשבח הקדש, adam miskaper beshevach Hekdesh, but still a
funny הלכה halakha that you have to pay out of pocket to
make sure. תא שמע, tasha shema, come in here. בשעת הפרשה יפה
סלע, Besha'at hafrasha yapheh selah, this is again the תוספתא, Tosefta, and
it says if when you set it aside it was worth one,
ובשעת כפרה יפה שתי סלעים, ubesha'at kapparah yapheh shtei selayim, and when
it was time for atonement it was worth two, יצא, yatza, you're
יוצא, yotzei, and again no qualification, of course the word לא lo
is here, but no in the תוספתא Tosefta it's not there. Anyway,
so no qualifications, it seems without any special cases, yes, it all
goes with how much it's worth at the time, not how much
it was worth when you bought it, not how much you invested
in it. If it's worth two שקל shekel even if some of
that value came once it was already sanctified.
But but now we're saying you still have to pay back the
difference though.
No, whether אדם מתכפר adam miskaper is did it work as a
קרבן. korban. It works as a קרבן korban whether you pay the
money or not. Is there a separate הלכה halakha pay? Yes, that
we're still saying. That's not the issue right now. בעי רבי אלעזר,
Ba'ei Rabbi Elazar, Rabbi Elazar asked, אדם מתכפר בשבח הקדש או לא?
adam miskaper beshevach Hekdesh o lo? So it seems like we just
got through that, but again here this was a question that Rabbi
Elazar framed it. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, so Rabbi Elazar,
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, כמה שנים גדל זה בינינו ולא
שמע הלכה זו ממני? kamma shanim gadal zeh beineinu velo shama halakha
zu mimeni?
I don't get it, Elazar you've been in our midst for so
many years, you never heard me teach this הלכה? halakha? You must
not have been paying attention. Oh, he was absent from class that
day. Okay, so anyway, so Rabbi Yochanan was a little astounded that
he didn't know the הלכה. halakha. מכלל דאמר רבי יוחנן אין, Mikhlal
de'amar Rabbi Yochanan in, yes, that Rabbi Yochanan says it does work.
Now of course you could say didn't you hear from me that
it doesn't? But when he says didn't you hear this הלכה, halakha,
it sounds like the הלכה, halakha, you know, the הלכה halakha is
אדם מתכפר. adam miskaper. That's like sounds like it's the it's the
issue. Is this the הלכה? halakha? And he says haven't you heard
this הלכה? halakha? אין. In. ועל הא דאמר, Ve-al ha d'amar, on
the following thing ר' יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said it works. דתנן Detnan
ולד תודה ותמורתה, Velad todah u-tmuratah,
if you have a child of a תודה, todah, right, because a
תודה todah can be a female or a תמורה, tmurah, remember תמורה,
tmurah, וכן המפריש תודתו ואבדה והפריש אחרת תחתיה ve-chen ha-mafrish todato ve-avda
ve-hifrish acheret tachteiha
or you lost your תודה, todah, you separated another one and then
you found the original. So the thing here that was sort of
the second one, the derivative one, not brought as the original תודה,
todah, אין טעונה לחם. ein teuna lechem. You bring it, it has
קדושת תודה kedushat todah but without bread because it's not the original.
ושלח ליה חנינא
משמיה דר' יוחנן, Ve-shlach lei Chanina mishmei d'Rabbi Yochanan,
that was the teaching, and then ר' חנינא Rabbi Chanina sent in
the name of ר' יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, here's ר' יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
לא שנו אלא לאחר כפרה. lo shanu ela le-achar kapara. All
when you do not bring bread, that's if you use the original
one for your תודה todah obligation and that had the bread as
a תודה todah has. Then the second one, the derivative, doesn't have
bread. דולד אין טעון לחם. De-vlad ein taun lechem. That's when you
don't bring bread with the ולד. vlad. אבל לפני כפרה, Aval lifnei
kapara, if you haven't brought the mother and you wanted to bring
the child for the תודה, todah, you could bring it, and therefore
in that case אבל לפני כפרה טעון לחם. aval lifnei kapara taun
lechem. You can bring the child for the תודה todah with the
bread. So if basically when does a child not get the bread?
When it's not the one functioning as the תודה. todah. But if
you didn't bring the mother, you could bring the child and then
it would get the bread. So what you see, you're יוצא yotzei
your obligation of a תודה todah with the child, which is a
שבח הקדש shvach hekdesh after the mother's been sanctified. The fact it
gives birth is a natural type of a increase of value and
nevertheless you can use that for your תודה. todah. אלמא קסבר Alma
kasavar you see he holds מתכפר בשבח הקדש, miskaper be-shvach hekdesh, you
can, that it does work. Now
that ends that discussion of מתכפר בשבח הקדש, miskaper be-shvach hekdesh, but
now that we had this funny phrase, I don't get it, you've
been learning with us so long you don't know the הלכה, halacha,
we're going to give a few more examples of that. Okay, בעי
ר' אלעזר, Ba'ei Rabbi Elazar, so ר' אלעזר Rabbi Elazar also asks.
בעלי חיים נדחים או לא? Ba'alei chayim nidachim o lo? If an
animal that's sanctified as a קרבן korban and still alive, can it
be pushed off? Right, sometimes if it's not able to be used,
that gives it, that stigmatizes it so it can't be used again,
but maybe that's only true after it's dead. Maybe it's not true
when it's alive. What's the story when it's alive? אמר ר' יוחנן,
Amar Rabbi Yochanan, הרי כמה שנים גדל זה
בינינו, harei kama shanim gadal zeh beineinu, you've grown up amongst us
for all these years ולא שמעת הלכה זו ממני, ve-lo shamata halacha
zu mimeni, you haven't heard me teach this הלכה? halacha? Again, we
assume that means that the answer is yes. מכלל דר' יוחנן אמר
אין, Miklal d'Rabbi Yochanan amar in, that it does, that a בעלי
חיים ba'alei chayim even when it's alive it can be pushed away,
it can be stigmatized. דאמר ר' יוחנן D'amar Rabbi Yochanan בהמה של
שני שותפין, behema shel shnei shutfin, if you have an animal owned
by two partners. הקדיש חציו Hikdish chetzyo and you sanctify your half
as a קרבן. korban. Now obviously you can't have a half an
animal as a קרבן. korban. So that קדושה kedusha was not able
to function as a, you know, to function to allow it to
be brought. וחזר ולקח חציו Ve-chazar ve-lakach chetzyo and then you buy
the other half והקדישו ve-hikdisho and you sanctify the other half. קדושה
ואינה קריבה, Kedusha ve-eina kreiva, it has sanctity but it can't be
brought because it's already been sanctified in a way that doesn't work.
ועושה תמורה Ve-osa tmuara and you could, if you, it could make
a תמורה tmurah ותמורתה כיוצא בה, u-tmuratah k'yotzei bah, and the תמורה
tmurah would have the same status, that it's קדוש kadosh but not
קריב. kariv. שמע מינה תלת, Shma mina tlat, and from this we
learn three things. There's always three. שמע מינה בעלי חיים נדחים, Shma
mina ba'alei chayim nidachim, even though it's alive it's pushed off. Here
the animal's alive, but since its original קדושה kedusha wasn't able to
be used, even when it becomes able to be used because you
bought the other half and sanctified the other half, it remains unable
to be used. That's בעלי חיים נדחים. ba'alei chayim nidachim. ושמע מינה
קדושת דמים מדחה, Ve-shma mina kedushat damim madcha, even though the original
קדושה kedusha was not קדושת מזבח, kedushat mizbeach, it wasn't fit to
be brought, the original קדושה kedusha was only קדושת דמים, kedushat damim,
at the time it was sanctified it only had a value קדושה,
kedusha, not yet fit to be brought.
ושמע מינה יש דיחוי בדמים, Ve-shma mina yesh dichui be-damim,
דיחוי dichui can occur even only on value even when it's not
yet, was never fit to be brought.
Of course that's the קדושת דמים.
kedushat damim. So Rashi basically says it's the same. As I told
you before, these always come in threes and there's often a big
Tosafot to try to explain how two is different than three specifically
because this is a recurring phrase by בעלי חיים נדחים. ba'alei chayim
nidachim. But the basic point Rashi here basically says is yeah, two
and three are basically the same. So the point is not only
a בעלי חיים נדחם, ba'alei chayim nidcham, one case would be that
originally it was fit for the מזבח mizbeach and then came a
time it wasn't. Here it was never fit for the מזבח mizbeach
originally, it was only קדושת דמים kedushat damim and that still makes
it דיחוי. dichui. Let's just finish till the bottom here. בעי ר'
אלעזר. Ba'ei Rabbi Elazar. ר' אלעזר Rabbi Elazar asks again, ר' אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar asking so you know what the answer's going to be.
הוזלו טלאים בעולם מהו? Huzlu tlayim ba-olam mahu? Here's interesting and it
ties back to our משנה. mishna. Let's say it is impossible to
find a ram worth two שקל. shekel. What can you do? Can
you not bring a קרבן אשם korban asham because it has to
have a minimum cost of two שקל? shekel? And even if you
say I'll pay more for it, we've just said it's not what
you pay, it's what it's worth. So let's say there are no
rams of the right age that are worth two שקל, shekel, what
are you supposed to do? מי אמרינן Mi amrinan do we say
no, whatever, assumingly that you can't get that. מי אמרינן מבחר נדריכם
בעינן, Mi amrinan mivchar nidreichem ba'inan, at the end of the day
we need the best, ואיכא ve-ika and this is the best even
though it's not worth the minimum amount, but the fact that it's
the best should satisfy. או דילמא Od dilma or do you say
כסף שקלים בעינן, kesef shekalim ba'inan, no it's an absolute requirement that
it has to be worth two שקל, shekel, וליכא ve-leka and you
don't have it. So that
does. And we've never heard this הלכה *halacha*. Okay, so not like
haven't you heard it in our בית מדרש *beis medrash*, we never
heard this הלכה *halacha*. That's an interesting question and we don't have
a tradition about that. We've never actually discussed that until now. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says ולא *velo*, has he not discussed it? For
אמר רבי יוחנן אמר רבי שמעון בר יוחאי *Amar Rabbi Yochanan Amar
Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai*, מפני מה לא ניתנה קצבה במחוסרי כפרה *mipnei
ma lo nitna kitzva be-mechusrei kapara*, why does the תורה *Torah* give
a minimum only by an אשם *asham* and it doesn't give it
by those people that require a חטאת *chatas* in order to become
טהור *tahor*? Why is there no minimum? And the reason is שמא
יוזלו טלאים ואין להם תקנה לאכול בקדשים *shema yuzlu telaim ve-ein lahem
takana le-echol be-kodashim*, because maybe the rams or whatever the sheep will
become so low value that you won't be able to satisfy the
minimum. And if that were true by people that were that needed
it to become טהור *tahor*, they'll never be able to be טהור
*tahor*, they'll never be able to eat קדשים *kodashim*. So the fact
that you go a while without getting atonement isn't maybe such a
big deal, but the fact that you're withheld from eating קדשים *kodashim*
is. So therefore that's why the תורה *Torah* didn't give a minimum,
which makes it clear that in the places where the תורה *Torah*
did give a minimum like the אשם *asham*, even if it's impossible
to get something, you still can't bring it, the minimum is the
minimum. Okay, אימא *eima*, so what do you mean? So it's clear
you know the הלכה *halacha* is that you have to always satisfy
the minimum. So what do you mean we've never heard this הלכה
*halacha*? אימא לא לימדנו הלכה זו *Eima lo limadnu halacha zu*. Okay,
it's not we've never heard it, we've never taught it. Okay, and
here so he wasn't upset at רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*, maybe he
was upset at himself. You ask that question, טאקע *takeh*, we've been
learning all these years, I never taught you that הלכה *halacha*. The
גמרא *Gemara* says how could you say that, that he never taught
it? והא רבי זירא בר אדא מהדר תלמודיה כל תלתין יומין קמיה
*Ve-ha Rabbi Zeira bar Adda mahader talmudei kol taltin yomin kamei*, רבי
זירא בר אדא *Rabbi Zeira bar Adda* chazered his learning in front
of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* every thirty days. And somehow that means,
the גמרא *Gemara* assumes that means that if he's spending time to
review everything he learned from רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* would have filled in any gaps. So רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*
would have taught him this הלכה *halacha*. It's a little funny why
the גמרא *Gemara* assumes that. So how could you mean you've never
taught it? אימא לא נתבקשה הלכה זו בבית המדרש *Eima lo nitbaksha
halacha zu be-veis ha-midrash*. Fine, maybe I taught it to one or
two people, but it was never raised in the בית מדרש *beis
medrash*. Now, so as opposed to giving רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* a
hard time before that he didn't hear things that were discussed, here
he said, ah, that's a great question and we've actually never discussed
it in the בית מדרש *beis medrash*. Here's the answer. Okay, but
it's good that you asked it, we've never discussed it. And the
answer is yes, a minimum is a minimum even if you can't
find anything, you're stuck.
גופא *Gufa*, אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בר
יוחאי *Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai*, now just to
end this, מפני מה לא ניתנה קצבה במחוסרי כפרה *mipnei ma lo
nitna kitzva be-mechusrei kapara*, why did the תורה *Torah* not give a
minimum? שמא יוזלו טלאים ואין להם תקנה לאכול בקדשים *shema yuzlu telaim
ve-ein lahem takana le-echol be-kodashim*, because then they would be stuck, it
would be impossible to get something at the minimum and never be
able to eat קדשים *kodashim*. Now the problem is a lot of
things don't have a minimum. The only thing that has a minimum
is an אשם *asham*. A חטאת *chatas* doesn't have a minimum, nothing
has a minimum. So מתקיף לה אביי *maskif lah Abaye*, אלא מעתה
חטאת חלב תינתן בה קצבה דלכפרה אתיא *ela me-ata chatas chelev tinasen
bah kitzva de-le-chapara asya*, so if you think oh there could be
a minimum for an אשם *asham* because that's only about atonement and
there maybe so you'll be stuck a little longer, so why isn't
there a minimum for a חטאת *chatas*? That's also about atonement. ולאו
לאישתרויי באכילת קדשים הוא *ve-lav le-ishtruyei be-achilas kodashim hu*, and that's not
about eating קדשים *kodashim*. מתקיף לה רבא *maskif lah Rava*, אלא מעתה
אשם נזיר להוי ביה קצבה *ela me-ata asham nazir le-havei bei kitzva*,
why isn't there a minimum for an אשם נזיר *asham nazir*? It's
only only some אשמות *ashamos* are are two שקל *shekel*, some אשמות
*ashamos* do not have a minimum. דלבטלה הוא דאתי *de-levatala hu de-asi*,
and not only that, by an אשם נזיר *asham nazir* it doesn't,
now this is an extreme statement, it's coming for naught. It doesn't
mean naught, it's an obligation, but it means it nothing hinges on
it. Okay, the טהרה *tahara* doesn't hinge on it, the starting
of
the נזירות *neziros* doesn't hinge on it, it's just a חיוב *chiyuv*
but nothing hinges on it. So why not there say that give
a minimum? Okay, if you're basically saying that you'll give a minimum
when it when we don't care that you get stuck. דאמר רבי
יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בר יוחאי *de-amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon
bar Yochai*, אין לך דבר שבא לבטלה אלא אשם נזיר בלבד *ein
lach davar she-ba le-vatala ela asham nazir bilvad*, the only קרבן *korban*
that doesn't actually have anything that hinges on it, it's an obligation
but nothing depends on it, is an אשם נזיר *asham nazir*. So
why not give a minimum? קשיא *Kashya*. The גמרא *Gemara* ends with,
okay you're right, saying that there's no minimum because the תורה *Torah*
didn't want you to get stuck here is not a sufficient answer
because pretty much other than a few אשמות *ashamos*, nothing has a
minimum and nevertheless the תורה *Torah* you know you don't have a
consistent reason why nothing has a minimum. Actually the more interesting question
to phrase is the opposite: why did the תורה *Torah* give a
minimum by אשם *asham*? Because אשם *asham* is really the exception. Okay,
tomorrow we will wrap up.